Brewster Family Papers, 1882-1967
Sophia Smith Collection, Smith College
Brewster family papers
1882-1967
Brewster family
MS 21
10 boxes (4.38 linear ft.)
Sophia Smith Collection Smith College Northampton, MA
Traveler, author, English teacher, Smith graduate, and librarian. Papers are primarily those of Anna Gertrude Brewster and Mary Kate Brewster. Both sisters were devoted to theatre, particularly to the Academy of Music in Northampton. They also wrote several books and plays, some of which were published. Material documents world travel, and includes scrapbooks, photographs, diaries, correspondence, and the Brewster children's family newspaper.
Civil War veteran Major Charles Harvey Brewster (1833-1893) was a prosperous Northampton businessman. He originally sold windows, doors, blinds and paints, and later transformed the enterprise into a successful florist shop. He married Anna Williams (1843-1935) in 1868 and the couple had six children: Anna Gertrude, Mary Kate, Caroline Williams, Charles Russell, Harold, and Helen Campbell.
Anna Gertrude (1869-1967) attended local schools and graduated from Smith College in 1893. She began her teaching career soon after, holding positions in Brewster, Massachusetts and Nashua, New Hampshire before studying for a year at Oxford University (1906-07). She taught English at Northampton High School from 1907 until her retirement in 1940, after which she taught at the Northampton School for Girls. Anna Gertrude was a charter member of the Betty Allen Chapter of the DAR, served on the advisory board of the Young Women's City Club, and was a long-time Trustee of the Forbes Library.
Mary Kate (1871-1957) was an avid traveler and a prolific writer. She went twice to Australia (1893 and 1896) and later to the American West (1920-21); she also traveled often to other parts of the United States. Her great love was the theatre, and she was especially committed to the Academy of Music in Northampton. She wrote several books and plays, some of which were published, as well as a treatise on the cultural value of municipal theatre. She corresponded with various actors and wrote reviews for "The New York Dramatic Mirror". She reviewed Smith College theatre productions for the Daily Hampshire Gazette, the Springfield Republican and the Boston Globe, and also regularly contributed articles about topics of interest in Northampton to these newspapers.
Only two of Charles Harvey and Anna Williams Brewster's six children married. Harold married Margaret B. Cable and they had three children: Gertrude, George and Margaret. Margaret graduated from Smith in 1932 and married Alfred C. Chard; they had two children, James and Carol. Margaret Brewster Chard died in 1982. Helen Campbell Brewster married Karl Brownson Allured in 1919. Their only child, Jonathan (b. 1920), married Nancy Babcock, and they had four children: David, Karla, Caroline and Charles.
The Brewster Family Papers are comprised primarily of the papers of Anna Gertrude Brewster and Mary Kate Brewster, dating from 1882 to 1967. The collection includes biographical material, family photographs, diaries, scrapbooks and other memorabilia, correspondence, writings, and the Brewster children's family newspaper (1884-1885). Mary Kate's papers include records of her two trips around the world (1893-1894 and 1896-1897), typescripts of novels and plays, correspondence with family members as well as with actors and actresses of the day, and her newspaper articles and theatre reviews. Anna Gertrude's papers include personal diaries and family correspondence, as well as letters received from former students. Both sisters kept annual records of finances, books read, and letters written and received. In addition, Anna Gertrude generally kept a record of social calls received and returned in a given year. These notations are located at the back of the diaries.
This collection is organized into four series:
I. General Family Information
II. Mary Kate Brewster
III. Anna Gertrude Brewster
IV. Other Family Members
Series I includes general family information, articles about the Brewsters, photographs, and the children's newspaper. It is followed by Series II and III, the papers of Mary Kate Brewster and Anna Gertrude Brewster, respectively. In both series, diaries are arranged chronologically. Correspondence is divided into two sub-categories, family and other. Letters to and from Mary Kate during her two trips to Australia are filed separately. Writings are arranged by type and then listed alphabetically by title. Personal memorabilia appear at the end of each series. Series IV consists of correspondence and memorabilia of other family members.
Information on Use
Terms of Access and Use
The Papers are open to research according to the regulations of the Sophia Smith Collection.
Additional Formats
Diaries (1889-1927) of Mary Kate Brewster are available on the History of Women microfilm series (New Haven: Research Publications) available in the Sophia Smith Collection and Neilson Library, Smith College and through interlibrary loan.
History of the Collection
The Brewster Family Papers were donated in 1966 by Philip Butcher of Baltimore, Maryland. He obtained them through Carl Waltz of Northampton when Mary Kate and Anna Gertrude Brewster moved from their family home to smaller quarters.
Search Terms
Australia--Description and travel--Sources; Northampton (Mass.)--History--Sources; Brewster family; Teachers--Massachusetts--History--Sources; Theater, Municipal--Northampton (Mass.)--History--Sources; Theater--Reviews--History--Sources; Authors, American--20th century--Sources; Family--United States--History--Sources; Voyages around the world--History--Sources; Women travelers--History--19th century--Sources; Brewster, Anna Gertrude, 1869-1967; Brewster, Mary Kate, 1871-1957
Additional Information
Related Material
Related collections are located elsewhere in Northampton. The Forbes Library holds copies of newspaper articles written by Mary Kate Brewster for the Daily Hampshire Gazette (1907-1935), as well as articles about Anna Gertrude Brewster. Both sisters were knowledgeable about local history, and were frequently asked to lecture to local organizations. The Forbes Library (Northampton, MA) has copies of several of these lectures and papers, including a history of Northampton schools by Anna Gertrude (read before the Northampton Historical Society, April 26, 1946). In addition, the library has the original typescripts of "Early Days of St. John's Episcopal Church in Northampton" (1954) and "Early Public and Private Schools" (1954), both by Anna Gertrude Brewster. Historic Northampton holds the original Civil War letters of Charles Harvey Brewster, as well as memorabilia and a collection of family photographs. See also: When This Cruel War is Over: The Civil War Letters of Charles Harvey Brewster David
- SERIES I. GENERAL FAMILY INFORMATION
  - Genealogy (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Articles about the family (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Photographs (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Children's newspaper, 1884-85 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- SERIES II. MARY KATE BREWSTER
  - Diaries
    - 1 Jan 1889-31 Dec 1890 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - 2 Oct 1893-31 Dec 1894 (includes Australia) (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - 1 Mar-30 Jun 1896 (includes Australia) (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - 1 Jul 1896-30 Jun 1898 (includes Australia) (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - 1 Jan 1899-31 Dec 1900 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - 1 Jan 1902-31 Dec 1903 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - 1 Jan 1907-31 Dec 1909 (Box 2, Folder 11)
    - 1 Jan 1910-31 Dec 1911 (Box 2, Folder 12)
    - 1912 (Box 2, Folder 13)
    - 1914 (Box 2, Folder 14)
    - 1915 (Box 2, Folder 15)
    - 1916 (Box 2, Folder 16)
    - 31 Dec 1920-4 Dec 1921 (Box 2, Folder 17)
    - 1 Jan 1922-31 Dec 1924 (Box 2, Folder 18)
    - 1926, 1927, fragments (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Correspondence
    - To family
      - Anna Gertrude Brewster, 1890-1904, 1921 (Box 3, Folder 20)
      - Anna Williams Brewster, Caroline Brewster, Aunt Carrie, 1882, 1923, undated (Box 3, Folder 21)
      - Australia trip, 1893-94 (Box 3, Folder 22)
      - Australia trip, 1896-97 (Box 3, Folder 23)
    - From family
      - Australia trip, 1893-94 (Box 3, Folder 24)
      - Caroline Brewster, 1901; Charles Russell Brewster, 1921 (Box 3, Folder 25)
      - Harold Brewster, 1942-44 (Box 3, Folder 26)
    - From others
      - Arthur Allen, 1925-1947 (Box 3, Folder 27)
      - Frank Lyman, 1918 (Box 3, Folder 28)
      - Northampton Players, 1916-1930s (Box 3, Folder 29)
      - Miscellaneous, 1916, 1917, 1942, 1943 (Box 3, Folder 30)
  - Writings
    - Novels
      - Tasman and "The Interrogation" (published copies) (Box 3, Folder 31)
      - Blessington (typescripts)
        - Part I: "Death in the Office" (Box 4, Folder 32)
        - Part II: "Myella: A Nice Little Girl" (Box 4, Folder 33)
        - Part III: "Myella and the Hermit" & Part IV: "Giving Up" (Box 4, Folder 34)
        - Part V: "Lincoln's Daughter" & Part VI: "Seas of Delight" (Box 4, Folder 35)
        - Part VII: "Myella Married" (Box 4, Folder 36)
      - Swithin Living and Dead (typescript; unclear if Part I (pp. 1-29) is missing, or if MKB eliminated it in a revision) (Box 4, Folder 37)
      - They Sail the Wide Seas (typescript), 1942 (Box 4, Folder 38)
    - Plays
      - "Daily Bread: A Truth in Whimsey in Three Acts" (includes photocopies of criticism and suggestions from an unidentified person) (Box 4, Folder 39)
      - "Daily Bread: A Farce Comedy" (different version than Folder 39; possibly incomplete) (Box 4, Folder 40)
      - "Steward: A Play of the Sea" (Box 4, Folder 41)
      - "The Success"
        - typescript (Box 5, Folder 42)
        - carbon, incomplete (Box 5, Folder 43)
        - revised (Box 5, Folder 44)
        - carbon of revised version (Box 5, Folder 45)
    - Essays
      - Learned Ladies Today", "The Editor We Complain Of (Box 5, Folder 46)
      - "The Municipal Theatre in America" (Box 5, Folder 47)
      - "The Municipal Theatre in America" (photocopy) (Box 5, Folder 48)
      - "Theatre in Northampton" (Box 5, Folder 49)
  - Memorabilia
    - Guest Book, 1904-1950 (Box 6, Folder 50)
    - Theatre Programs (Box 6, Folder 51)
    - Attractions and bookings at Academy of Music, 1891-1912 (Box 6, Folder 52)
    - Scrapbooks (2): Clippings of newspaper articles; correspondence with editors, and clippings from theatre programs (Box 6)
- SERIES III. ANNA GERTRUDE BREWSTER
  - Diaries
    - 1882, 1884, 1885 (Box 7, Folder 53)
    - 1 Jan 1889-31 Dec 1892 (incomplete journal through May 7, 1890; beginning on page 58, AGB kept a line diary for the remainder of 1890, and for the years 1891 and 1892) (Box 7, Folder 54)
    - 1886, 1887, 1897 (Box 7, Folder 55)
    - 28-30 Jun 1888, 14 Jul 1888 (Box 7, Folder 56)
    - 1893, 1894, 1895 (line diary) (Box 7)
    - 21 Jul-19 Aug 1894, 3-31 Aug 1895, 8 May-5 Oct 1898, 9 Apr-17 Jun 1899 (?) (Box 7, Folder 57)
    - 1903, 25 Feb-28 Aug, 1922 (trip to Europe) (Box 7, Folder 58)
    - 1 Jul-26 Aug 1937 (trip to England) (Box 7, Folder 59)
  - Correspondence
    - To family
      - Anna Williams Brewster, 1899-1907 (Box 8, Folder 60)
      - Caroline, Helen, and Charles Harvey Brewster, 1906-37 (Box 8, Folder 61)
      - Mary Kate Brewster, 1906-37 (Box 8, Folder 62)
      - "Aunt Kate" and "Ortie", 1876 and 1898 (Box 8, Folder 63)
      - Unidentified fragments (Box 8, Folder 64)
    - From family
      - Anna Williams Brewster, 1872-1906, undated (Box 8, Folder 65)
      - Caroline Brewster, 1882-1906, undated (Box 8, Folder 66)
      - Charles Harvey Brewster, 1871-1889 (Box 8, Folder 67)
      - Charles Russell Brewster to Anna Gertrude, 1904-05, 1921 (Box 8, Folder 68)
      - Harold Brewster, 1887-1909 (Box 8, Folder 69)
      - Helen Brewster, 1897-1920 (Box 8, Folder 70)
    - From others
      - 1877-90 (Box 8, Folder 71)
      - 1890-95 (Box 9, Folder 72)
      - 1895-1900 (Box 9, Folder 73)
      - 1901 (Box 9, Folder 74)
      - 1902-05 (Box 9, Folder 75)
      - 1906 (Box 9, Folder 76)
      - 1907 (Box 10, Folder 77)
      - 1908-30, undated (Box 10, Folder 78)
      - George Cable, undated (Box 10, Folder 79)
  - Writings: Miscellaneous, undated (Box 10, Folder 80)
  - Memorabilia: DAR membership certificate (photocopy) (Box 10, Folder 81)
    [See original in Flat File]
- SERIES IV. OTHER FAMILY MEMBERS
  - Charles Russell Brewster: Diary, 1906 (Box 10, Folder 82)
  - Correspondence
    - Anna Williams Brewster to Caroline and Harold 1899, 1901, undated (Box 10, Folder 83)
    - Miscellaneous, 1893, 1905, 1918, 1924 (includes fragment) (Box 10, Folder 84)
    - Caroline Brewster to Anna Williams Brewster, 1899, undated (Box 10, Folder 85)
    - Charles Russell Brewster to Anna Williams Brewster, 1904, 1905 (Box 10, Folder 86)
    - Harold Brewster to Anna Williams Brewster, 1905, 1906, 1926 (Box 10, Folder 87)
    - Harold Brewster to Helen Brewster, Caroline Brewster, 1902-03, 1920 (Box 10, Folder 88)
    - Helen Brewster to Anna Williams Brewster, 1903, 1904, undated (Box 10, Folder 89)
    - Margaret Brewster Chard to Caroline Brewster, 1948 (Box 10, Folder 90)
  - Memorabilia: Helen Campbell Brewster Allured's scrapbook of theatre programs (Box 10, Folder 91)
  - Drawer 12: Anna Gertrude Brewster, DAR Membership Certificate (Map-case Flat File:)